<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>17196360</Do_id>
  <Journal>European journal of surgical oncology : the journal of the European Society of Surgical Oncology and the British Association of Surgical Oncology</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Gastrointestinal stromal tumours: clinical overview, surgery and recent advances in imatinib mesylate therapy.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>To review the clinical features of gastrointestinal stromal tumours (GISTs), the role of surgery and its principles and molecular targeted therapies.;A Medline-based literature search on relevant topics was performed in PubMed for key articles concerning the clinical features, biology and the novel strategies in the management, whether surgical and/or pharmaceutical, of gastrointestinal stromal tumours. Some information was obtained from Proceedings of the American Society for Clinical Oncology published recently.;Surgical resection, the first-line intervention for operable GISTs, was historically the only effective treatment. For residual, metastatic and/or inoperable disease, treatment options remain under intense and continuous scrutiny. However, their molecular genetics, i.e. the mutations of the genes coding for KIT or platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha, two receptor tyrosine kinases, have been targeted for therapeutic intervention by imatinib mesylate -- a tyrosine kinase inhibitor.;Treatment of GISTs with imatinib has led to dramatic improvements in progression-free and overall survival, thereby rendering its use in the preoperative and postoperative treatment under intense investigation. New investigational agents are being developed and participation in promising clinical trials remains a standard of care.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Benzamides;Piperazines;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Pyrimidines;Imatinib Mesylate</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Benzamides;Clinical Trials as Topic;Combined Modality Therapy;Drug Resistance, Neoplasm;Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors;Humans;Imatinib Mesylate;Piperazines;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Pyrimidines;Treatment Outcome</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>drug therapy;surgery;pharmacology;therapeutic use;pharmacology;therapeutic use;pharmacology;therapeutic use</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
