<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>17625570</Do_id>
  <Journal>Nature</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Identification of the transforming EML4-ALK fusion gene in non-small-cell lung cancer.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Improvement in the clinical outcome of lung cancer is likely to be achieved by identification of the molecular events that underlie its pathogenesis. Here we show that a small inversion within chromosome 2p results in the formation of a fusion gene comprising portions of the echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML4) gene and the anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) gene in non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cells. Mouse 3T3 fibroblasts forced to express this human fusion tyrosine kinase generated transformed foci in culture and subcutaneous tumours in nude mice. The EML4-ALK fusion transcript was detected in 6.7% (5 out of 75) of NSCLC patients examined; these individuals were distinct from those harbouring mutations in the epidermal growth factor receptor gene. Our data demonstrate that a subset of NSCLC patients may express a transforming fusion kinase that is a promising candidate for a therapeutic target as well as for a diagnostic molecular marker in NSCLC.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Cell Cycle Proteins;EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Microtubule-Associated Proteins;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;anaplastic lymphoma kinase;EML4 protein, human;Serine Endopeptidases</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>3T3 Cells;Amino Acid Sequence;Animals;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Cell Cycle Proteins;Cell Proliferation;Cell Transformation, Neoplastic;Chromosome Inversion;Chromosomes, Human, Pair 2;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Mice;Microtubule-Associated Proteins;Molecular Sequence Data;Mutation;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Serine Endopeptidases</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>drug therapy;genetics;metabolism;pathology;genetics;metabolism;drug effects;genetics;pathology;genetics;genetics;drug therapy;genetics;metabolism;pathology;genetics;metabolism;genetics;antagonists &amp; inhibitors;chemistry;genetics;metabolism;antagonists &amp; inhibitors;genetics;metabolism;genetics;metabolism</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
