<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>18519520</Do_id>
  <Journal>Haematologica</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Development of hypogammaglobulinemia in patients treated with imatinib for chronic myeloid leukemia or gastrointestinal stromal tumor.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Imatinib mesylate is a tyrosine kinase inhibitor used as first line treatment in chronic myeloid leukemia and gastrointestinal stromal tumor patients. Although several in vitro and animal studies demonstrated that imatinib affects immune response, few immune alterations are described in humans. We retrospectively studied hematologic and immunological parameters in 72 chronic myeloid leukemia and 15 gastrointestinal stromal tumor patients treated with imatinib at standard dosage and in 20 chronic myeloid leukemia patients treated before the introduction of imatinib in clinical practice. Both chronic myeloid leukemia and gastrointestinal stromal tumor patients developed a significant reduction of gammaglobulin and immunoglobulin serum levels. No significant hypogammaglobulinemia was observed in chronic myeloid leukemia patients in the pre-imatinib era. These data demonstrate that imatinib treatment induces hypogammaglobulinemia that can reach a severe entity in 10% of cases, both in chronic myeloid leukemia and in gastrointestinal stromal tumor patients. Prospective studies are needed to evaluate immune humoral alterations and to define the real incidence of infectious events, including viral reactivations.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Antineoplastic Agents;Benzamides;Immunoglobulins;Piperazines;Pyrimidines;gamma-Globulins;Imatinib Mesylate</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Adult;Agammaglobulinemia;Aged;Aged, 80 and over;Antineoplastic Agents;Antineoplastic Combined Chemotherapy Protocols;Benzamides;Female;Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors;Humans;Imatinib Mesylate;Immunoglobulins;Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive;Male;Middle Aged;Piperazines;Pyrimidines;Retrospective Studies;gamma-Globulins</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>chemically induced;adverse effects;therapeutic use;therapeutic use;drug therapy;therapeutic use;drug therapy;adverse effects;therapeutic use;adverse effects;therapeutic use;therapeutic use</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
