<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>23060582</Do_id>
  <Journal>Anticancer research</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Clinical outcomes of thoracic radiotherapy for locally advanced NSCLC with EGFR mutations or EML4-ALK rearrangement.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Little is known about the occurrence and consequences of epidermal growth factor receptor gene (EGFR) mutations and the fusion of the echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML4) and anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) genes in locally advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).;We retrospectively examined 37 patients with locally advanced NSCLC treated with definitive thoracic radiotherapy (TRT). Characteristics were compared among patients classified positive for EGFR mutations, EML4-ALK rearrangement, or patients who were double-negative for these changes.;We identified 11 (29.7%) patients with EGFR mutations and 3 (8.1%) with an EML4-ALK rearrangement. Progression-free survival of patients with EGFR mutation-positive NSCLC was similar to the one of those with double-negative disease (13.1 and 18.6 months). The incidence of local recurrence was higher in EGFR mutation-positive patients with NSCLC than in double-negative NSCLC.;EGFR mutations and the EML4-ALK rearrangements were detected in substantial proportions of patients with locally advanced NSCLC. The efficacy of TRT was limited in patients with EGFR mutations.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Antineoplastic Agents;EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;EGFR protein, human;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Adenocarcinoma;Aged;Antineoplastic Agents;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Chemoradiotherapy;Disease-Free Survival;Female;Gene Rearrangement;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Male;Middle Aged;Mutation;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;Retrospective Studies;Treatment Outcome</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>drug therapy;genetics;mortality;radiotherapy;therapeutic use;genetics;mortality;radiotherapy;drug therapy;genetics;mortality;radiotherapy;genetics;genetics</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
