<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>24585406</Do_id>
  <Journal>Annals of surgical oncology</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Pemetrexed-carboplatin adjuvant chemotherapy with or without gefitinib in resected stage IIIA-N2 non-small cell lung cancer harbouring EGFR mutations: a randomized, phase II study.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs) show great efficacy in patients with advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) with EGFR mutations. The efficacy and safety of gefitinib following adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with EGFR mutation are unknown.;In this open-label, phase II study, patients with resected stage IIIA-N2 NSCLC harbouring EGFR mutations (either exon 19 deletion or L858R point mutation) were assigned randomly to receive pemetrexed (500 mg/m(2)) and carboplatin (AUC = 5), administered every 21 days for 4 cycles, followed with or without gefitinib (250 mg/day) for 6 months. The primary end point was disease-free survival (DFS).;From August 2008 to September 2011, 60 patients were included in our center. DFS was significantly longer among those who received pemetrexed and carboplatin (PC)-gefitinib than among those who received PC alone [hazard ratio (HR), 0.37; 95 % confidence interval (CI) 0.16-0.85; P = 0.014; median, 39.8 vs. 27.0 months]. The rates of 2-year DFS were 78.9 % in the PC-gefitinib group and 54.2 % in the PC alone group. The rates of 2-year overall survival (OS) were 92.4 % in the PC-gefitinib group and 77.4 % in the PC alone group (HR, 0.37; 95 % CI 0.12-1.11, P = 0.076). The most common adverse event was rash (43.3 %, 13/30) in the PC-gefitinib group and the administration of gefitinib following chemotherapy was well tolerated.;The administration of gefitinib following PC adjuvant therapy shows significant improvement in DFS in patients with resected stage IIIA-N2 NSCLC harbouring EGFR mutations.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Glutamates;Quinazolines;Pemetrexed;Guanine;Carboplatin;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;gefitinib</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Adult;Aged;Antineoplastic Combined Chemotherapy Protocols;Carboplatin;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Chemotherapy, Adjuvant;Disease-Free Survival;Female;Glutamates;Guanine;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Male;Middle Aged;Pemetrexed;Pneumonectomy;Prospective Studies;Quinazolines;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;Survival Rate</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>adverse effects;therapeutic use;administration &amp; dosage;genetics;secondary;therapy;administration &amp; dosage;administration &amp; dosage;analogs &amp; derivatives;genetics;pathology;therapy;administration &amp; dosage;adverse effects;genetics</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
