<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>24674157</Do_id>
  <Journal>Lung cancer (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Sensitive and specific detection of EML4-ALK rearrangements in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) specimens by multiplex amplicon RNA massive parallel sequencing.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Recurrent gene fusions of anaplastic lymphoma receptor tyrosine kinase (ALK) and echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML4) have been recently identified in ∼5% of non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLCs) and are targets for selective tyrosine kinase inhibitors. While fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) is the current gold standard for detection of EML4-ALK rearrangements, several limitations exist including high costs, time-consuming evaluation and somewhat equivocal interpretation of results. In contrast, targeted massive parallel sequencing has been introduced as a powerful method for simultaneous and sensitive detection of multiple somatic mutations even in limited biopsies, and is currently evolving as the method of choice for molecular diagnostic work-up of NSCLCs.;We developed a novel approach for indirect detection of EML4-ALK rearrangements based on 454 massive parallel sequencing after reverse transcription and subsequent multiplex amplification (multiplex ALK RNA-seq) which takes advantage of unbalanced expression of the 5' and 3' ALK mRNA regions. Two lung cancer cell lines and a selected series of 32 NSCLC samples including 11 cases with EML4-ALK rearrangement were analyzed with this novel approach in comparison to ALK FISH, ALK qRT-PCR and EML4-ALK RT-PCR.;The H2228 cell line with known EML4-ALK rearrangement showed 171 and 729 reads for 5' and 3' ALK regions, respectively, demonstrating a clearly unbalanced expression pattern. In contrast, the H1299 cell line with ALK wildtype status displayed no reads for both ALK regions. Considering a threshold of 100 reads for 3' ALK region as indirect indicator of EML4-ALK rearrangement, there was 100% concordance between the novel multiplex ALK RNA-seq approach and ALK FISH among all 32 NSCLC samples.;Multiplex ALK RNA-seq is a sensitive and specific method for indirect detection of EML4-ALK rearrangements, and can be easily implemented in panel based molecular diagnostic work-up of NSCLCs by massive parallel sequencing.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Adult;Aged;Aged, 80 and over;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Female;High-Throughput Nucleotide Sequencing;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Male;Middle Aged;Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Sensitivity and Specificity;Sequence Analysis, RNA</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>genetics;methods;genetics;methods;analysis;genetics;methods</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
