<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>25096400</Do_id>
  <Journal>International journal of oncology</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Hypoxia induces resistance to ALK inhibitors in the H3122 non-small cell lung cancer cell line with an ALK rearrangement via epithelial-mesenchymal transition.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) with echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML4)-anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) rearrangements generally respond to ALK inhibitors such as crizotinib. However, some patients with EML4-ALK rearrangements respond poorly to crizotinib. Hypoxia is involved in the resistance to chemotherapeutic treatments in several cancers, and we investigated the association between the responses to ALK inhibitors and hypoxia. Sensitivity of the H3122 NSCLC cell line (EML4-ALK rearrangement) to ALK inhibitors (crizotinib or alectinib) was investigated during a normoxic or hypoxic state using an MTT assay. We found that the cell line was resistant to the inhibitors during hypoxia. Hypoxia mediated morphologic changes, including cell scattering and the elongation of the cell shape, that are characteristic of the epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT). A migration assay demonstrated that the number of migrating cells increased significantly during hypoxia, compared with during normoxia. Regarding EMT-related molecules, the expressions of slug, vimentin, and fibronectin were increased while that of E-cadherin was decreased by hypoxia. In addition, hypoxia inducible factor 1A-knockdown cancelled the hypoxia-induced EMT and resistance. Our findings indicate that hypoxia induces resistance to ALK inhibitors in NSCLC with an EML4-ALK rearrangement via the EMT. </Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Cell Cycle Proteins;Microtubule-Associated Proteins;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;anaplastic lymphoma kinase;EML4 protein, human;Serine Endopeptidases</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Cell Cycle Proteins;Cell Hypoxia;Cell Line, Tumor;Cell Proliferation;Drug Resistance, Neoplasm;Epithelial-Mesenchymal Transition;Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Microtubule-Associated Proteins;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Serine Endopeptidases;Signal Transduction</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>drug therapy;genetics;pathology;genetics;drug effects;drug effects;drug therapy;genetics;pathology;genetics;genetics;pharmacology;genetics;genetics;drug effects</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
