<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>25360721</Do_id>
  <Journal>PloS one</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Clinicopathologic features of patients with non-small cell lung cancer harboring the EML4-ALK fusion gene: a meta-analysis.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>The frequencies of EML4-ALK fusion gene in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) with different clinicopathologic features described by previous studies are inconsistent. The key demographic and pathologic features associated with EML4-ALK fusion gene have not been definitively established. This meta-analysis was conducted to compare the frequency of the EML4-ALK fusion gene in patients with different clinicopathologic features and to identify an enriched population of patients with NSCLC harboring EML4-ALK fusion gene.;The Pubmed and Embase databases for all studies on EML4-ALK fusion gene in NSCLC patients were searched up to July 2014. A criteria list and exclusion criteria were established to screen the studies. The frequency of the EML4-ALK fusion gene and the clinicopathologic features, including smoking status, pathologic type, gender, and EGFR status were abstracted.;Seventeen articles consisting of 4511 NSCLC cases were included in this meta-analysis. A significant lower EML4-ALK fusion gene positive rate was associated with smokers (pooled OR = 0.40, 95% CI = 0.30-0.54, P&lt;0.00001). A significantly higher EML4-ALK fusion gene positivity rate was associated with adenocarcinomas (pooled OR = 2.53, 95% CI = 1.66-3.86, P&lt;0.0001) and female (pooled OR = 0.61, 95% CI = 0.41-0.90, P = 0.01). We found that a significantly lower EML4-ALK fusion gene positivity rate was associated with EGFR mutation (pooled OR = 0.07, 95% CI = 0.03-0.19, P&lt;0.00001). No publication bias was observed in any meta-analysis (all P value of Egger's test &gt;0.05); however, because of the small sample size, no results were in the meta-analysis regarding EGFR gene status.;This meta-analysis revealed that the EML4-ALK fusion gene is highly correlated with a never/light smoking history, female and the pathologic type of adenocarcinoma, and is largely mutually exclusive of EGFR.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>genetics;pathology;genetics;pathology;genetics</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
