<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>25611025</Do_id>
  <Journal>Current opinion in oncology</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Second and third-generation epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors in advanced nonsmall cell lung cancer.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>The first-generation epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors (EGFR-TKIs), gefitinib and erlotinib, are effective as first-line treatment of advanced nonsmall cell lung cancer (NSCLC) harboring activating EGFR mutations (deletions in exon 19 and exon 21 L858R mutation). EGFR T790 M resistance mutation (EGFR T790 M) ultimately emerged in most of these patients. The second and third-generation EGFR-TKIs were designed to have more potent inhibition of EGFR and to overcome EGFR T790 M. This review describes the recent developments of these novel EGFR-TKIs.;The second-generation EGFR-TKIs, afatinib and dacomitinib, irreversibly bind to the tyrosine kinase of EGFR and other ErbB-family members. Afatinib has been approved as first-line treatment of advanced NSCLC harboring activating EGFR mutations. Dacomitinib is under development. Third-generation EGFR-TKIs, AZD9291, CO-1686, and HM61713, inhibit both EGFR activating and resistance mutations, while sparing wild-type EGFR. In early-phase studies, these drugs demonstrated promising response rates against tumors with acquired EGFR T790 M.;Second-generation EGFR-TKI, afatinib, is available as first-line treatment of advanced NSCLC harboring activating EGFR mutations. Third-generation EGFR-TKIs are under development for tumors harboring acquired EGFR T790 M.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Antineoplastic Agents;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Quinazolines;Erlotinib Hydrochloride;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;gefitinib</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Antineoplastic Agents;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Drug Resistance, Neoplasm;Erlotinib Hydrochloride;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Mutation;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Quinazolines;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>administration &amp; dosage;drug therapy;genetics;immunology;drug effects;drug therapy;genetics;immunology;administration &amp; dosage;administration &amp; dosage;antagonists &amp; inhibitors;antagonists &amp; inhibitors</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
