<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>26019170</Do_id>
  <Journal>Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association for Cancer Research</Journal>
  <Doc_title>Induction of PD-L1 Expression by the EML4-ALK Oncoprotein and Downstream Signaling Pathways in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>Therapies targeted to the immune checkpoint mediated by PD-1 and PD-L1 show antitumor activity in a subset of patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). We have now examined PD-L1 expression and its regulation in NSCLC positive for the EML4-ALK fusion gene.;The expression of PD-L1 at the protein and mRNA levels in NSCLC cell lines was examined by flow cytometry and by reverse transcription and real-time PCR analysis, respectively. The expression of PD-L1 in 134 surgically resected NSCLC specimens was evaluated by immunohistochemical analysis.;The PD-L1 expression level was higher in NSCLC cell lines positive for EML4-ALK than in those negative for the fusion gene. Forced expression of EML4-ALK in Ba/F3 cells markedly increased PD-L1 expression, whereas endogenous PD-L1 expression in EML4-ALK-positive NSCLC cells was attenuated by treatment with the specific ALK inhibitor alectinib or by RNAi with ALK siRNAs. Furthermore, expression of PD-L1 was downregulated by inhibitors of the MEK-ERK and PI3K-AKT signaling pathways in NSCLC cells positive for either EML4-ALK or activating mutations of the EGFR. Finally, the expression level of PD-L1 was positively associated with the presence of EML4-ALK in NSCLC specimens.;Our findings that both EML4-ALK and mutant EGFR upregulate PD-L1 by activating PI3K-AKT and MEK-ERK signaling pathways in NSCLC reveal a direct link between oncogenic drivers and PD-L1 expression.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>Antigens, CD274;EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;RNA, Messenger;Phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinases;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;anaplastic lymphoma kinase;Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-akt</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Antigens, CD274;Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Cell Line, Tumor;Cell Membrane;Gene Expression Regulation, Neoplastic;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;MAP Kinase Signaling System;Mutation;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Phosphatidylinositol 3-Kinases;Proto-Oncogene Proteins c-akt;RNA, Messenger;Receptor Protein-Tyrosine Kinases;Receptor, Epidermal Growth Factor;Signal Transduction</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>genetics;genetics;metabolism;metabolism;genetics;metabolism;drug effects;metabolism;antagonists &amp; inhibitors;metabolism;antagonists &amp; inhibitors;metabolism;genetics;metabolism;genetics;metabolism;genetics;metabolism;drug effects</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
