<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Do_id>26107243</Do_id>
  <Journal>Asian Pacific journal of cancer prevention : APJCP</Journal>
  <Doc_title>A Pooled Analysis on Crizotinib in Treating Chinese Patients with EML4-ALK Positive Non-small-cell Lung Cancer.</Doc_title>
  <Doc_abstract>This analysis was conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety of crizotinib based regimens in treating Chinese patients with EML4-ALK positive non-small-cell lung cancer.;Clinical studies evaluating the efficacy and safety of crizotinib based regimens on response and safety for Chinese patients with EML4-ALK positive non-small-cell lung cancer were identified by using a predefined search strategy. Pooled response rate (RR) of treatment were calculated.;In crizotinib based regimens, 3 clinical studies which including 128 Chinese patients with EML4-ALK positive non-small-cell lung cancer and treated with crizotinib based regimen were considered eligible for inclusion. Pooled analysis suggested that, in all patients, the pooled RR was 59.3% (76/128) in crizotinib based regimens. ALT/AST mild visual disturbances, nausea, and vomiting were the main side effects. No treatment related death occurred in these crizotinib based treatments.;This pooled analysis suggests that crizotinib based regimens are associated with good response rate and accepted toxicities in treating Chinese patients with EML4-ALK positive non-small-cell lung cancer.</Doc_abstract>
  <Doc_ChemicalList>EML4-ALK fusion protein, human;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Pyrazoles;Pyridines;crizotinib</Doc_ChemicalList>
  <Doc_meshdescriptors>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung;Clinical Trials as Topic;Humans;Lung Neoplasms;Meta-Analysis as Topic;Oncogene Proteins, Fusion;Prognosis;Protein Kinase Inhibitors;Pyrazoles;Pyridines</Doc_meshdescriptors>
  <Doc_meshqualifiers>drug therapy;genetics;drug therapy;genetics;genetics;therapeutic use;therapeutic use;therapeutic use</Doc_meshqualifiers>
</Document>
