<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Document>
  <Meeting_name> Prognostic value of the most frequent mutations in GIST</Meeting_name>
  <Doc_title> Prognostic value of the most frequent mutations in GIST</Doc_title>
  <Background>['Background', ' More than 80% of gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) have KIT or PDGFRA mutations, of which more than 100 different types have been published. Several studies have investigated the prognostic value of these mutations, however most were retrospective and mixed several mutations together. We investigated the prognostic value of the most frequent mutations. Methods', ' Patients with GIST were prospectively included in MolecGIST study (#A10535, ASCO 2009). We selected the 9 most frequent mutations, and a 10th group of patients with a deletion within PDGFRA exon 18 (18del). These patients accounted for 45% of those for which mutations were available. Results', &quot; The 9 most frequent mutations were KIT AY502- 503dup (n=26), V559D (n=25), 557-558del (n=23), W557R (n=14), V560D (n=13), L576P (n=11), V559G (n=7), 560del (n=6), and PDGFRA D842V (n=30). 18del group included 17 patients. Metastases were present at diagnosis in 20 (12%) patients. Evolution after surgical resection was available for 138 other patients, with a median follow up of 2.3 months. 58% of the patients had intermediate or high Fetcher's risk, and 30 of them received Imatinib as adjuvant treatment. GIST recurrence occurred in 12 patients. The 3 relapsing patients of the adjuvant group had AY502-503dup (n=2) and W557R. The 9 others had AY502-503dup (n=2), V559D (n=1), 557-558del (n=1), L576P (n=1), V559G (n=1), D842V (n=1) and 18del (n=2). GIST malignancy (metastasis or relapse) was associated with the type of mutation (p=0.024, Fisher's exact test). Mutations AY502-503dup, 557-558del, V559G and 18del were of high risk (33% malignant), D842V, V559D, L576P, W557R were of low risk (10% malignant), and those involving V560 were of very low risk (0/17 malignant). Conclusions&quot;, ' The precise type of KIT and PDGFRA mutations is predictive of malignancy in GIST, and mutations involving adjacent amino acid may have very different prognostic value.']</Background>
</Document>
